hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
iding Our Guest today is Sebastian R an
independent app developer from Germany
who created habit kit on the podcast we
talked with Sebastian about quitting a
job to build his own apps going back to
that job after failing to gain traction
and the inflection point that allowed
him to finally quit for good hey
Sebastian thanks so much for joining us
on the podcast today hi thank you for
having me I'm a huge fan of the podcast
and of Revenue kid of course oh bless
you and Jacob nice to have you back on
the podcast a long time without you has
it been the production schedule for
subclub is confusing and out of my sight
but I assume I assume I'm on every
episode is that not the case are there
episodes without
me we got talk we got to talk about this
I did some live episodes and then go
very good I listen to every single one
I'm not on I promise of course you
better
all right so Sebastian I wanted to kick
things off today so you're a career web
developer but now a solo IND the app
developer so how did you get started in
apps as a web developer the motivation
behind building mobile apps was actually
because I decided to start my own app
business I just wanted to work on my own
products and sell them on the Internet
and make a living of it and all the
ideas that I had were all related to
best suiting for the mobile platform and
that's how I initially got excited for
mobile app development it does feel like
apps are a great Market not just that
like you were saying that the idea but
as a Marketplace and having access to so
many consumers directly through the app
stores were there not any Web projects
that you thought would be successful or
was it just kind of more exciting to
build apps versus your bread and butter
kind of web development
yeah so this whole web development thing
always felt a little bit more
intimidating to me as a solo
entrepreneur you have to build this back
end then and you have to deal with
payments and sales tax and stuff like
that and when you're on the mobile
platform all this payments and sales tax
thing is handled by Apple and Google and
that was really a good point for me to
start there and yeah the ideas as I
already said before yeah it makes it
much more appealing I feel like in webd
or like building Indie web apps you see
much more like prosumer or utility SAS
kind of stuff and a lot less consumer
lifestyle focused things so it's almost
like if you want to build stuff for
consumers for people the web's not a
great option right like mobile is like
clearly a better and then of course like
all the stuff that you discuss like
payments like having a merchant of
record all of that stuff and if you're
in consumer all of those problems are
much more multiplied because like if
you're selling B2B your number of
customers is usually much much lower
right you might be at hundreds if you're
doing well and in that case like you're
dealing fewer jurisdictions and your
compliance is maybe a little bit easier
but when you're dealing with consumers
it's thousands right and now you're
multiplying that problem so yeah it's
almost not even an option to do a
consumer web app yeah and back when I
started habit kits I already got this
idea a couple of years ago for this app
and back then when you scroll down all
the way on my Twitter profile and look
at my first post you can actually see me
building a very early web version of
habit kit and I actually completely
abandoned this because habit tracking
didn't feel natural to me on the web so
it felt much more better well I mean you
could build it as a progressive web app
I'm sure but then you lose the
distribution you lose all the things
that make it nice about being mobile
this is like one of those controversial
opinions I feel like a pwa can never
really totally feel as nice as a swift
or even flutter or some sort of native
back mobile app I don't think that's a
controversial op it like I still think
some I mean obviously there people who
chose to use that technology to like die
on that hill but price $1,000 the person
can put a pwa in front of me and me not
figure out it's a pwa like I guarantee
you I will know yeah so you mentioned
wanting to build your own stuff and
there is kind of always that Allure of a
side project of like having something
going on on the side but was it always
the goal to like leave your job what's
so bad about having a day job I guess
the first time that I thought about
building my own apps was at the end of
my University time when I was writing my
Master's thesis and at that time I
discovered the Indie hackers.com
community and learned about all these
cool people that are building their own
products and selling them on the
Internet and actually make a living of
it and that felt super cool and exciting
to me and although I took a real job as
a software engineer after University the
thought of bootstrapping my own business
really got stuck at the back of my head
so after 3 years of working for that
company we were basically Contracting
for this other company and building
their enterprise resource planning back
office s why why would Indie hacking
seem appealing if you were doing that
all
day yeah so I guess it's the nature of
Contracting work you have very limited
control about how the product You're
Building will look like how it will
behave what's the ux and the UI and the
only thing that you're mostly having
control of is the technical side as a
programmer in this project and I'm not
really the type of developer that
unconditionally loves programming I'm
definitely not the type of software
engineer that Geeks out on optimizing
algorithms or something like that which
also doesn't feel like something you're
often doing when you're programming an
Erp for an internal use case yeah
exactly I'm the type of developer that
likes to make his own Concepts and how a
problem should be solved and then
develop it myself and then see the
concept in the real world and yeah so I
got a little bit bored by this project
that I couldn't really escape from and
don't get me wrong the job was fine and
I learned a lot met many cool people but
at this time I wanted to try my own
stuff was it also just kind of like
having an outlet like working this job
where it sounds like as a consultant
it's like you just got handed specs like
you were even getting to like interact
with a product team or be in the
meetings where things were decided and
stuff so was it somewhat just like I
have to build things it sounds like
that's your deeper motivation was like
creativity and just wanting to like
build products yeah in the end the most
important aspect was this creativity
thing I guess some jobs can definitely
make that possible but it's usually not
the case in the Contracting World maybe
I would have been better off at a
company where they developed their own
product I hope you can confirm that but
I can imagine that the developers at
Revenue C can bring in their own ideas
and have a real impact on the product
right sure sure I think though there
maybe the moment it got ruined for you
is when you found any hackers.com
because I think once somebody gets the
idea that they need to do this or they
want to do this like all of the rest of
it feels like you're just finding the
justification to go do it when really
it's just you want to go do it right
it's just something you need to do and I
try to tell that to folks that you know
you're in Tech long enough and this goes
between Venture back startups down to
like Indie side projects going
independent all of that stuff I think if
you feel the need to do it like you have
it in you like it's inside of you and
you just need to go do it you can spend
all the time you want justifying it
building up the whatever things you got
to do to convince yourself it's okay but
like the real decision is made up is
like is it inside you and do you have to
do it if it's like ah it'd be nice it'
be cool but whatever like do not do it
do not do it because like nine times out
of 10 maybe it's worked out well for you
I don't know but like it doesn't net out
but it will be successful if like you
had to do this and then at least even if
it fails like you did it right you got
it out of you and you can decide then
like you have clear eyes about what you
want to do with your life and do you
value the things that because I guess
like to you like reading the Indie
hackers he was cool but like what about
it was appealing to you beyond the like
having creative control over what you're
building yeah so it's all about building
a cool lifestyle business for myself I
want to work whenever I want I want to
take breaks whenever I want if life gets
in the way something is with the family
I want to be there and want to have my
business there and don't touch it but
it's somehow should run by its own this
passive income thing I know it's not
passive but I just like rental
properties right very passive very
passive for anybody who's ever owned a
rental property knows it's very passive
I mean I just took a three week vacation
and didn't have to do a single thing for
my business and it just continued to
work yeah wow I had somewhat a different
experience on the Indie hacker side in a
way because I started the business first
and just like jumped off a cliff but I
will say for those kind of listening to
this while that is the dream and
Sebastian has done it well for me it was
like over a decade of just grinding and
this was before subscription so it's
always paid up front and then you know
my apps often would get a lot of press
and then it was always like okay when am
I going to get the next press and so you
know I had a lot of flexibility and got
to take some time as needed but I think
it depends on your personality and
backup financially and other things as
to whether even once you start to
achieve some level of success you can
take that as a luxury versus like having
this constant and and I had four kids
along the way so like for me there was
like this just constant fire under me
I'm saying this to kind of maybe balance
out the perspective is that there was
just a constant fire and so then even
though I did see some level of success I
never took a 3 we vacation was pretty
awesome so early in your journey that
you were able to really take that time
off I mean for me it was just always ah
what's next what's next and just
grinding grinding grinding I think it's
a big personality thing I see this in
entrepreneurs outside of tech a lot of
times too like folks that own cash
flowing businesses and things like this
like some of them are really good about
actually using it to like lever into a
lifestyle that they want others it just
becomes worse than a job because like a
job you can quit
or you can get fired right like there
are outs that are like accessible to you
but sometimes with these businesses
there isn't and there's like Sebastian
when you're gone for 3 weeks did no
customers get mad nobody like came up or
they did and you're just like you know
what they'll live what's your philosophy
for like creating these boundaries I
usually get two or three emils a day at
this season in winter it's a little bit
more but in summer it's just three or
four emails per day and it's mostly
feature requests people saying hey I
love your app but it would be cool if
you could add that and that's not really
an email I have to reply to but you're
looking at them yes did you look at them
okay okay see there's always there
always in the lifestyle they don't tell
you this on Indie hackers you're out on
your yach for three weeks or whatever
but you are checking right and I I was
checking yeah yeah did you even respond
to some of them after I was back
here you're really on trial now
Sebastian it's Indie hacker
but I think it's a good point and like
obviously that doesn't feel intrusive to
you which I think also with a job can be
very different sometimes right like with
a job if you're on vacation or you're
doing something and like the job tries
to seal some of your time like that
feels much more offensive sometimes when
it's your own thing you're like well
this is my own thing and I own it and
like I have to do this and it doesn't
necessarily feel like work but again
it's so psychological like depending on
the person and the mindset and that same
for like your job like some people don't
mind having to like take care of things
for their job when they're like
ostensibly out other people it's like
the worst in the world and it really
just depends on your mindset and
personality and stuff like that I don't
even know necessarily that there's a
better or worse way to approach it but I
do think it's interesting because well
we haven't got to this yet because you
got into Indie life and then you got out
of Indie life is that correct not really
because my app Business didn't really
start as a side project because I
actually quit my job to start my own
business most Indie hackers tell you as
device don't do this only do this when
you have a stable income from your side
Hustle but I actually did the opposite
and left my comfortable job and then
started my app Business how did that
work financially you just kind of saved
up and were single and kept your
expenses low or how' you jump off that
Cliff I had this safety net that I built
up before I knew that at least as an
experienced software developer here in
Germany it isn't really hard to find a
real job again if the business goes
downhill so I got that safety I built up
some savings that I could live off for
at least a year and at that time I
didn't have many Financial Obligations
of course I had to pay for an apartment
and food and stuff like that but I
didn't have kids no loans for a house or
something like that so I was basically
free to do whatever I want yeah this is
hard to reason about for most people
like conceptualization of risk right
when you are near the bottom and that's
not the bottom like life's pretty good
you have an apartment you have all these
things but like you don't have debt you
don't have obligations you don't have a
lot of stacked leverage on yourself
personally like you can jump off a cliff
and you're only falling a foot right
like but even if you don't have a lot of
assets like if you have to declare
bankruptcy your credit's screwed but
like what are they going to take right
like you don't have any asset you know
most banks wouldn't give you loans and
most of the time you're not going to end
up in owing money that you can't pay but
you really especially early in life it's
just a fact there's less at stake and
that's often the time it's best to start
something thing but on the flip side
it's also like you probably know the
least you're like least experienced and
things like this and I'm counseling
somebody I know who's 21 years old and
he's like thinking about starting a
business right now but it's obviously
there's a lot of considerations and I'm
like I almost just like do it like do it
because like even if you don't know what
you're doing if it fails you put some
stuff in your experience bag if it
succeeds holy crap if you started a
business that compounds at 21 years old
like you could retire by the time you're
35 if you really wanted to if works out
well right like to be able to start that
so early in your life is such an
advantage but again there's no free
lunch right so doing it early versus
doing it later like all has its
trade-offs I do think there's something
to like talking to a lot of
entrepreneurs I think there Sound Advice
in like saving and making it safe before
you can take a leap but and I'm curious
how this motivated you but I think when
you jump off the cliff even if you have
some safety net you know whatever I
think jumping before you have a rope to
grab onto is is a good motivator right
it sort of like has to work you know
what I mean like how did you feel about
that jumping off with nothing in Hand by
the time you were independ that yeah
that definitely felt scary and weird but
I also additionally to all the safety
nets that I mentioned earlier I also
said to myself okay I time boox this app
Business experiment to exactly 12 months
it seemed reasonable to me to have this
backup plan if it doesn't work out and I
said to myself okay if this doesn't work
out I will go back to my old job or
another job and what was your bar for
definition of working out did you have
like a number or like something in mind
that you said like oh this is successful
so the condition was to reach the base
level which I could live of some indie
hackers College Ramen profitability yeah
yeah but I actually didn't reach it and
so I left on good terms with my previous
employer and then actually even got back
to them once were over yeah I had to
admit defeat and then had to was it
tough did you have a lot of Pride and
was it tough for you to go back and do
that or did you just feel like hey I set
myself this thing like how was that
psychologically for you to kind of have
to go back that wasn't really so bad
because in my free year I learned so
many great things I got so much
self-confidence I developed this two
cool apps and a lot of people downloaded
them already and that really developed
my selfconfidence so going back wasn't
really that bad I even got a nice ways
and yeah it was a great decision you
there you go folks a minimum you can
come back and renegotiate your salary so
during that year though like how did
things go like did you already have like
an app in mind when you quit or was it
like you quit and like okay now I got to
pick the product let's talk through that
first year and like how you built stuff
when I made the decision to start my own
business I didn't really have a good
idea what app to build I think in the
end the first idea isn't really that
important what's more important is to
start moving and just build anything it
doesn't really matter what because once
you started building something you'll
automatically get new better ideas start
writing that's like the famous thing for
writing too it's like just start writing
just start writing and then even if you
throw it away you're more likely not
you're going to wander onto something
good right yeah just get into the flow
I'm sure it activates certain of your
brain that are responsible for
creativity or something like that when I
quit my job I took a look at my personal
life and tried to figure out what app
doesn't meet my requirements and I
quickly decided that I want to build my
own version of a fitness tracking app
yeah sounds really boring there are
already 100 slightly competitive market
yeah yeah there are already a million
other Fitness tracking apps but I just
wanted to start moving and that's why I
picked this idea that's how I came to
build my first applift bear with this
one year it's ultimately a lot of time
so like you could have and I would have
been the person doing this work for 12
months and then ship the app did you
like have a deadline like I got to get
this in the app store by X day so that I
know whether it's going to work or not
so that I can iterate like how did you
set deadlines and set expectations in
that 12-month period I already followed
lot of other Indie hackers and I I read
some advice and I already knew that I
shouldn't develop this app for 12 months
and then release it and then see that
nobody really cares about it I just was
disciplined enough to buckle down and
then develop it in the first two months
of my free year and then launch it so I
didn't really had a problem with this
yeah you have to have low expectations
about what you're going to produce I
think uh realistic expectations not
necessarily low expect no low I say low
I should find I I saw a first version of
Revenue cap screenshot again the other
day and it looks
terrible and like honestly like I think
not to toot my own horn or whatever but
I think a lot of people would have
trouble shipping that and like I just
don't care what people think like you
know or like what the majority of people
think or something like this right like
with your point Sebastian it's like just
do something and I guess the flip side
is like maybe you're concerned about
your perception of yourself and what you
can create that's one problem I think
other people are just ered like oh what
are people going to think about me and
the thing is is like even if it's crap
nobody pays attention if you ship
something crappy it's fine because a few
people might notice and a few people
might be this is crappy but also like
most people just won't notice and they
won't care and then you make it nice
over time and then more people are
exposed to it as it gets better and
better now there's flip sides if you're
like the Humane team or like other teams
like this where you have a lot of
Spotlight on you your initial launch
really matters but you're not the Humane
team like you're most people aren't that
right you can just kind of shipped
something I think it's great like two
months that's a really good timeline to
get something into production and start
learning yeah we kind of spoiled the
ending because you went back to your job
but what was the reception for Lift bear
and how did things go at launch and then
the rest of that year as you were
already saying Jacob setting
expectations is really important not
only in terms of what you're producing
also in terms of what the reception be
of your first app so lift bear wasn't
really a success it was a very quiet
launch when I released it I didn't have
many Twitter followers back then and I
was and still am by the way a huge
beginner when it comes to marketing so
yeah that was tough I only got a couple
of downloads but I was proud to finally
have my own app on the App Store and
Google Play that was that was a huge
milestone yeah you got to the App Store
you download it you see your name there
are some users somebody downloaded it
right I'm sure and you said a couple of
people literally two people downloaded
it it were more but okay in the first
week maybe 100 and after that only 10
per week or something like that yeah
which then it's like 10 activate five
actually open the app two actually
finish onboarding and then those all
turn in a week right so it's below the
minimum threshold for something that's
actually being used right but in some
ways that's actually incredible though
it's like you built something and like a
100 random strangers around the world
found it and downloaded it and then 10
people a week around the world I mean
the power of the app store right it's
like people are searching even if you're
like number 50 on the list in a search
or whatever it's background radiation
the app store right find it yeah when
you saw those numbers you now say like
you're a bad marketer you didn't think
about growth did you go like oh I have a
growth problem like what was your
diagnosis because at some point six
months in maybe you're in the store you
know the numbers are not great like what
did you do or try or what was your next
move yeah so after this very quiet
launch of course I still got feedback
from friends and a couple of Twitter
followers and from my family because I
myself used the app daily I decided not
to give up on it immediately and then I
continued developing cool new features
because that's what developers do you
know how to do yeah yeah yeah clearly I
need more features clearly the problem
is the feature set so I added cool stuff
like statistics and new exercise types
and stuff like that there is a logic to
that right like there is a logic to
build cool things as a method of growth
but you also have to have a channel to
like tell new people that that feature
exists right because even if the 10
people that downloaded are incrementally
more happy from that feature like it's
not going to create a growth engine you
know yeah exactly that's pretty tough
yeah I did that roughly for six months I
also tried to optimize the store listing
doing some ASO try to do some marketing
on Instagram and I even tried app search
ads but the app wasn't going anywhere
actually and after 6 months I couldn't
take it anymore I could look back on
roughly $100 of Revenue made totally in
the six months brutal right wow yeah so
that's cool because I made $100 with my
f but I knew if I want to continue
working on this app business I
definitely your personal burn rate I
assume is a little bit higher than that
I definitely I mean if it makes you feel
any
Revenue cat 12 months in oh about 12
months in I think we had made
$300 right so like SAS typically has a
lower start rate but still we were in
that same position I remember Miguel and
I just being like this will never work
like 300 and 10,000 are so far apart in
mentally right that you're just like
this will never work right so I can
totally understand that's very
demoralizing at the beginning when you
have just really small numbers and like
if you put it in the context of like
you'll spend $100 on a nice dinner right
it becomes really kind of
brutal yeah yeah and that's exactly the
point where you need to make the
decision do I do something different
with the same product or do I pivot it
completely into a new product or or do I
go back to work or do I got back to work
yeah but that wasn't the part where I
went back to work I still had six months
in my fre oh okay okay okay got it after
all this lift bear depression I actually
decided to focus on a new project then I
wanted to do it as an experiment I set
myself a very small deadline of two
months of building it and yeah that's
how I built my second app habit kit
which was way more successful then did
you know right away when you launched it
was it like night and day between the
two launches or when did you know that
maybe this was a better try it was
actually before the launch of the app I
was building in public on Twitter and
the first time that I posted a picture
of the main screen of habit kit this
post totally blew up and I actually got
800 likes that was a lot for me back
then that was the moment when I knew
okay this could be more successful than
lift bear interesting what about that
post because like that could just be a
fluke but there must have been something
right like most of my posts don't get
that let's and they're great in my
opinion what was it was it just like hey
here's what I'm building or was it like
hey I'm launching this like what was the
nature of it that you think made it so
interesting to people yeah so I guess
the text was just here this is the new
app that I'm building that's the main
screen and then I posted the main screen
of habit kit where you see the grid with
the color tiles and stuff like that for
your habits that was it and people seem
to resonate with it they really liked it
and I don't know why but it actually
went through the roof okay yeah I mean
that's product Market fit right or
that's something which growth does not
matter as much if you have product
Market at least like growth is not
requisite for some amount of success if
you have product Market fit I.E like
people are going to pull your product
out of you you can kind of wait and
defer the like growth aspects and in
fact like every Jewel of effort or
dollar of effort you put into growth is
going to be multiplied by more the
better your product is and so that's
really where you want to start it's hard
to quantify the value of those signals
but it's something right like this is
the challenge with product Market fit or
like validating do I have an interesting
product especially before you have a
product fully deployed and people using
it in real measures of metrics you
really do have to look at these
anecdotal qualitative things and does
seem valid so that had to be really
encouraging while you're like
pre-production to get that sort of
response yeah that was awesome this is
eight months in now of your year of
Indie but you still ended up going back
to your job so I'm assuming the launch
didn't go quite as well as maybe the
kind of one tweet blowing up indicated
it could so in the first month after
releasing habit kid K I made more money
than in the last 6 months combined so
that was a huge win but yeah so the
first 6 months of habit kits I made
roughly $
1.5k in total revenue per month but the
sad part was that my self-imposed
deadline of 12 months was over and the
revenue wasn't that great as I hope did
you think about breaking your rules yeah
I faced a tough decision to actually
continue
or returning back to my previous job but
that's a that's a decision I think
people don't realize it's not just like
do I start a thing there's a lot of
these points especially in the early
days before you hit traction and then
even like throughout the life of
business it's like okay I got this far
do I double down do I keep investing
especially if you're like unprofitable
like you're burning right it's like okay
do I think there's a bet here that I can
keep pouring into or is it time to like
cash in my chips and give up or change
strategy if I had known What would then
I wouldn't have returned to my o job so
it's always a really tough decision and
it was actually pretty scary to continue
burning for my savings it's real money
and ex you're German you can't break the
rules I wasn't going to say it we don't
do stereotypes here but I was likeing
very feel like a very D thing to be like
I can't I made a rule I cannot break
it was it almost to the day or month
like you went back like right at the 12
months or you kind of saw the writing on
the wall and were kind of ramping toward
it yeah it was exactly 12 months I
started my free year in April and went
back in April again wow so you're back
at your job but habit kid now you have a
side project how did that go working
full-time and working on habit kit on
the side I have to say I wanted to
continue working on my apps on the site
so I decided to work only 4 days a week
for my previous employer that's a nice
perk like that's not always super
possible in a lot of gigs so that was
great yeah that was really great and
that allowed me to take Fridays off and
have this whole day for my own apps
where I could continue improving my apps
and do what I do that was awesome so I I
went back to my old job and after two
months or so something really great
happened actually I remember back then I
was at a friend's wedding on a Saturday
and suddenly my phone started buzzing
with a crazy frequency of notifications
and when I checked that were actually
sales notifications from revenue C and I
quick checked some stats and then I saw
that habit kit finally started to wank
in the top five for a big keyword on the
App Store and Google Play that led to
Crazy growth in downloads and revenue um
really so it was like one incremental
step up the like search rankings and
then that changed it it felt like it yes
the fold is a real thing right being
above the fold and below the fold is a
real thing was that a change you made on
the ASO side or was it an algorithm
change that boosted you up no I actually
didn't change anything back then for 3
months or so I didn't change anything so
it wasn't a direct change outcome from
something wow was that a little
unsatisfying to me like I'm successful
but I don't know why and I have no
control over it uh no actually it felt
really great okay good good you're a
happier person than I am I had
absolutely no regrets it felt more like
ah finally
I
yeah I always knew it was great yeah
exactly so that's two months into the
job at what point did you hit Ramen
profitability and then think okay now I
really can quit I guess that was at the
start of fall the end of summer in
September I have to check the numbers
but I guess that was the first time I
reached multiple thousands of dollars in
Revenue that led me to make the tough
decision again should I continue at my
job or should I quit and go fulltime
again on this Indie hacker thing that
was the point I had to take a couple of
months to think about it because I
really felt bad I really felt sorry for
my employer and I had some great friends
at the company and they were really
engaged to bring me back and yeah I felt
really bad but with these numbers I
honestly had no other choice to so was
that fall of 2022 or or was that just
this last fall 2023 that was last fall
yeah exactly okay wow and so you've been
posting publicly and we'll get to that
here in a sec but I know all your
numbers because you post like you have a
whole blog with weekly reviews and all
that so you ended 2023 with 120,000
downloads and $51,000 in Revenue not a
bad year for this side project that
happened to blow up yeah exactly
especially you account for my salary as
a software engineer additionally that I
had for the second half of the year yeah
so that was a absolutely crazy year and
looking back it even got crazier in
January and February of this year yeah
so I was looking again I was looking at
your numbers prepping for this
conversation and again you post it all
publicly so just for the listeners
benefit though so you quit in the fall
and went full-time and then I want to
ask like why you think this happened but
what happened was in the first two
months of 2024 you did 60k so almost
10,000 more than the whole 2023 just
January and February and then in March
April and May you did another 51k so in
those three months you did the full
amount that you had done the previous
year but you had already even done 60k
so you're at
110k of Revenue in 2024 so far
incredible
congratulations what happened like you
quit in the fall you had some momentum
coming in but what was that inflection
point that this really became a real
thing in 2024 I started ranking for the
App Store and Google Play for this big
keywords in May and back then from last
winter I didn't have any points any
numbers of the revenue because I just
hadn't gotten to the reach that I have
today so I couldn't really compare and
didn't know what would come in Winter I
guess it's in the nature of habit
tracking apps that it's heavily
influenced by seasonality so at the
start of the Year lots of people make
resolutions for the new year start new
hobbies or just generally want to
improve themselves so that's a huge
factor I guess and that led to the
incredible have new number wow so it
wasn't new marketing it wasn't adding
features to the app it was that you had
built this base of a good enough product
that people liked it and were willing to
pay for it and then you I guess locked
into combination of building a good
product and the algorithms shining
favorably upon you got this momentum in
search then it was just the organic
search and the spike from the new year
and so the inflection point was again
somewhat out of your control that's the
beauty of the App Store and Google play
I mean you get all this Impressions and
reach for free basically and they do all
the marketing don't have anything to do
with it you developed any relationship
with apple editorial or anything like
that have they given you features or any
of the like editorialized stuff not at
all I applied through their form for
being featured and stuff like that but
it never really happen so I'm still
waiting for that it's really interesting
are you doing anything to like Leverage
because I think one of the easy come
easy go with these algorithm things
right like are you worried about another
algorithm change or like maybe just you
falling down the rankings like how do
you think about that as a risk to what
you have that's definitely a hug point
I'm really afraid or scared of this
algorithm changes but I I have my ASO
basics in place I think I didn't do any
mistakes so I'm sure that if I don't
make a very big mistake in crashing back
to the app or something like that that I
won't fall down that much in this
ranking I hope so at least I mean it can
be durable especially as your review
base like builds up and like your mini
brand and I don't know how the ASO
algorithms work exactly but I the more
clickthrough and I know they use usage
as well as a proxy so if you have good
retention in your product that that gets
factored in so like again it sucks it's
a black box like you don't know what's
going on but you hope that it's aligned
to like the correct incentives like I'm
sure Apple wants that like they want
correct like user incentives I don't
know if they use subscription retention
I wouldn't be surprised I don't know why
they wouldn't use that as well as a
metric obviously they should be
promoting apps that make them more money
right like that would be smart for them
business-wise but yeah there is always
this fear you live by the app stores
algorithms you die by the app stores
algorithms and I don't know the answer
for Indie for where you're at because
you could try to build your own
acquisition channels and maybe that's
worth experimenting with and maybe you
have experimen with Asa but even going
beyond that but that suddenly expands
just the scope of what you do you said
you experimented with Instagram ads but
let's say you wanted to like experiment
with that like you can't just be like
I'll make a crappy ad and put it on Tik
Tok like you have to like invest in that
as if it's a whole project right like
what is going to get people interested
like what is about my app that's
interesting like how do I make this work
otherwise you'll lose money like it just
won't be a profitable Enterprise yeah I
should definitely do this or hire people
to do this but right now I'm focusing on
being creative and do the things that
are fun to me right now I'm isn't a
terrible isn't a terrible algorithm
right like it's not a terrible algorithm
because at least you're going to do it
with energy right as opposed to if doing
Tik Tock ads is not something that
sounds fun to you don't do it because
you'll probably do a bad job exactly
that probably feel like work again and
being here at home and focus down on my
products and make them better that
doesn't feel like worked for me which
like also I mean the recurring
subscriptions right like you have
recurring subscriptions even if Apple
dropped you out of the top you know
ideally like you're retaining these
people maybe even you're capturing the
ability to Market to them you're also
building your like Indie presence right
you're becoming more of a known thing
right you're not just getting the cash
and the downloads like you're turning
this into Brands you're turning it into
install base and like all those things
are somewhat durable and there's always
chances to like capitalize on that which
you don't have when you're leaving your
job for the first time with zero right
in revenue and to Jacob's point from
earlier is that now that you have that
level of product Market fit and some you
have a channel now ASO is your channel
and so like what Jacob was saying
earlier it's like you need the channel
you need some pull and when you have
that pull and a channel then building
features is actually maybe the best
thing to do is it in until you see signs
that you're dropping in the algorithm
and maybe at some point it would be a
night and day difference where you wake
up one day and you're out of the top
five and you're not getting that many
downloads but even then it's like you'd
probably drift to 10 and now you're
getting half the downloads or whatever
like it's not going to be night and day
drop but now that you have that kind of
buffer and the pull in the market
building a really great app
experimenting with monetization and
stuff like that probably is a way better
use of your time yeah maybe and I also
have this other channel that we didn't
talk about so I was building my apps in
public and I have actually grown a
following on X and nowadays LinkedIn
even if Apple decides to down rank habit
kit I always have this audience of
people that would for me that are
engaged with me and that want to help me
I can always use that to build a new app
or boost a new app to better wanking on
stuff Community I mean Community is
super durable it's why we do this
podcast it's why those activities are
very valuable if you can content that
people find interesting and they want to
be a part of it I was going to ask I was
browsing to the app I don't think you
collect any contact information in the
app is that correct yeah nothing yeah
which like there's good reasons to do it
and not to do it but like collecting
some way of communicating with that user
base is really valuable as well so like
let's say the ASO floor drops out from
under you you can re-engage that user
base you can send them and be like hey i
s new features or like you could even
add and I'm just giving app advice that
you don't want but like you can always
add like a sign up for the The Habit kit
newsletter like sign up for email
updates and make it very optin right you
can make it very light that's one thing
even with Revenue cat I've been
surprised is like we were building
contact list for a long time but we
weren't really marketing to it heavily
but then I learned like yeah shipping
stuff is great but you have to tell
people about it too or like it doesn't
really connect you can connect those two
things like building new features that
are interesting and then telling the
people who should care that's really
magical and that can create this real
flywheel effect of like re-engaging
existing users and it can be really
durble but that's always my biggest
thing with people who are very
successful from the App Store is like
okay use this momentum to find some way
to be successful without the app store
because like it might not always be
there yeah definitely that's a good
point I got this email list thing on my
to-do list my to-do list is very long um
yeah
sure yeah you talked about the
advantages of building a public like
building up a community and like having
an audience to Market to a little bit
although maybe the audience You're
Building isn't necessarily people who
are going to be subscribers or whatever
but what are some of the other
advantages and disadvantages you've seen
building in public the way you have
building in public has definitely been
one of the best decisions that I made
while building this app Business the
benefits you will immerse yourself in
this really cool community of other
builders and creators developers
designers and you get to know them meet
up with them or partner up with them and
you can draw a lot of motivation and
inspiration from each other so when I'm
feeling down and I'm not really in the
mood of building new stuff or something
like that I open Twitter and see my
friends building other cool apps and
features I instantly get motivated to do
this myself that's a huge aspect of it
at the start when you're releasing a new
app you will get a lot of feedback which
is super important even if it's not
super durable right like it's just
something some eyeballs some comments
that's you usually really helps with
improving the first version or it gives
you at least a point or where to move
next and then have you seen some
disadvantages there are some
disadvantages but I think that the
advantages definitely outweigh them but
sure when people see that you can make
that much money with a relatively Simple
app like habit kit for example it
doesn't take too long until people start
copying your apps concept or even
shamelessly start copying your design
blog by block that's downside but I
usually try to ignore this copycats and
focus on my own stuff yeah and and the
thing is whether you build in public or
not people can see the data on sensor
Tower yeah you might make it happen a
little bit faster by being more visible
but the advantages outweigh them and
we've never committed at Revenue cat to
being fully open right so it's just
different but we have been I think
probably more open than most and for the
same reasons it's like hey like we build
for Builders so it's like a thing to
talk about people like to see what we're
building and how we're building and it
creates a community and like you know
once in a while you say something or do
something that has some push back or
some blowback and like you deal with it
you apologize or you issue a retraction
or whatever maybe this is just a
uniquely me problem this might be a me
problem it hasn't happened that many
times right but I think in general you
know if anybody's paying attention to
you that's always you know no press is
bad press I honestly think that goes
pretty far if people are talking about
what you're doing and you're okay with
what you're doing ethically like I think
it's all positive to be out there put
yourself out there yeah sure you also
get all those mean comments sometimes or
there are always these people that know
everything better and in every post it's
always interesting though none of them
are more successful than you are that's
really funny is that how that works it's
just for some reason it's always the
less achieved people who have less to
show for it that know all the answers I
don't know there's some correlation
there some yeah they are always smarter
than me yes yes yes that can be quite
intimidating especially when you yeah if
you haven't actually you don't have
anything in hand right like you haven't
actually proven the ability to build
something those comments can seem we
have this one famous we made stickers
for it for the team this one Reddit user
who when we posted our launch thread
called us a ripoff middlemen made easy
because our tagline was in app
subscriptions made easy and I have it
screenshotted and I share it in slack
fairly frequently anytime we have some
amount of success but when we posted
that it was 2017 like we had no Revenue
we had no apps we had nothing and so
this Rando on the internet calling me
that I was like oh you know who is this
person like what do they know like do
they know more than me and you take it
seriously and then it takes a while
until you don't but I guess the advice
for anybody is just never take the hater
seriously I mean unless like literally
all you get is haters then maybe maybe
listen there is some there is some limit
there but like maybe don't always just
post through it I always save this stuff
because like I find it super motivating
like I keep it for the haters I have
like a haters folder of all the like
hateful comments people have said about
Reven cat and I'm like you know what I'm
just going to use that for fuel oh
that's funny I have the opposite folder
I only yeah the
POS Different Strokes for different
folks so whatever it
takes that's probably more diagnosis of
psychological profiles than any Myers
Briggs Test could ever
do yeah well speaking of unsolicited
from people who are less successful than
you the last thing I wanted to touch on
was your pricing because I think it's
way too low raise your prices so I'm
curious if you've done any price
experimentation and kind of what your
pricing philosophy 99 cents a month geez
99 cents a month six bucks a year or $15
lifetime I was going through the app I
had already downloaded it before but not
paid ton of attention to your
monetization but when we're talking
about you coming on the podcast I was
looking at your pay wall and all that
kind of stuffff like whoa whoaa wait a
minute he's like successful Indie
charging $6 a year what's going on here
so yeah what's your pricing philosophy
when I released the first app of habit
kit that felt like the fair pricing
point to me and after that I was adding
feature after feature and lots of cool
stuff and I always said to myself okay
after the next feature or update you
will raise your prices and I didn't do
it yeah
that's it it's on my to-do list and and
okay before you do the email list you
know what you're in this position where
you could just double it just double it
$2 a month that's still really low and
like nobody's gonna get mads a year keep
doubling it until your haters folder
gets too big and then then take it back
and Notch I had this app that I sold uh
Windows app for Microsoft flight
simulator that I launched in like 2011
for like $4 or something like this I
wrote it in a weekend all it did was
like take one socket it connected an
iPad app forf iPad app to Microsoft
flight simulators this really nich
utility and it was before Indie hacking
had a name whatever I just put it up
there's this thing gumroad that had just
launched I put it up there $5 a month
and just sold a bunch and a bunch and a
bunch and I had all the support I was
like oh geez whatever and eventually I
was like so annoyed of all the support I
was having to do I was just like I don't
want any more I don't want anybody to
download this anymore so I made it $20 a
month zero change in
downloads nobody was like I probably
could have made it $50 and everybody
would have still paid because of course
it's like of the niche now habits are
different right you probably couldn't
Forex and maybe not see anything but
that was to me like the most visceral
experience of not really being able to
understand the price value curve right
like as a developer you can't really
feel it until you actually take in data
points you know yeah I think there are
always two kinds of people some people
say hey habit kit is way too inexpensive
you should double your prices and then
there are people usually get reviews on
Google Play that say $1 a month for this
app never that's a little bit
intimidating but yeah I should
definitely I mean by definition that
person has no value to
you they probably would never buy this
yeah they're never going to buy it and I
mean that's also being on Android is
another you know you can't look at your
price leverage on Android and iOS the
same right they're very different
communities maybe don't double on
Android but I would put money on the
fact that if you doubled your prices you
would make double the money that's a
50/50 I'd say 50-50 over under on that
one I it's pretty likely that that's the
case yeah at that price point yeah 12
bucks a year two bucks a month well if
there is a tool out here Sebastian that
would let you run that price experiment
fairly low effort so I know a guy let me
know if you're interested in trying it
out but like you could actually test
this I heard about it yeah I I will
definitely do it move that to the top of
your to-do list and then share on
Twitter and in your weekly log how
things turn out
but yeah as we wrap up was there
anything else you wanted to share we're
going to put links to your blog where
you do your weekly updates to the app to
your Twitter profile and Linkedin yeah
anything else you wanted to share as we
wrap up not really yeah that would be
great check out my apps and my Twitter
and leave it with well this was a ton of
fun we haven't done this kind of Indie
success story in a while and I'm like
all fired up man it's so cool to see oh
no David's going David's going to give
himself a toet deadline and quit quit
your job I've already already got my app
out
there my weather up app has been doing
really well this year and it is really
fun having I miss having an app I will
say I miss having an app I miss having
an app a little bit even though I have a
you know big SAS whatever but like there
is something special magical about
having your own little app like it's fun
it's great it is all right well thanks
so much for joining us it was so fun
chatting through all this and best of
luck I think you're going places like I
think you've got a great little business
here it's not going to be so little a
year from now and then a year from that
some of the other folks we had on like
Curtis Herbert it's like he did $10,000
his first two years and now he's doing
over a million dollars a year so it's
crazy how these things can scale from
little side projects and Indie hacking
to real businesses you know it sounds
like you don't want to like hire people
and do that kind of thing but you can
build a great lifestyle business yeah
yeah really crazy I'm excited for the
time to come and yeah thank you for
having me and I wish you all the best
for having you kid of course I will use
in every other app I make there we go
there's the clip thank you
Sebastian thank
you thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community
[Music]